Alexander S. Henderson papers, 1888-1963 (bulk 1900-1954)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Alexander S. Henderson papers, 1888-1963 (bulk 1900-1954)
AZ 027
Henderson, Alexander S., 1859-1944
Chiefly records of the A.S. Henderson general merchandise store in Patagonia, Arizona, from 1900 to 1940 including inventories, correspondence, merchandise ads, ledgers, monthly account books, and bills.
11 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Henderson was a merchant in Patagonia, Arizona.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
Series I: A.S.Henderson Store Records, 1907-1940
Series II: Mining Records and Correspondence, 1911-1954
Series III: Property Records and Investments, 1900-1963
Series IV: Alexander S. Henderson, Personal Materials, 1899-1958
Series V: Eva Henderson, Personal Materials, 1888-1961
Series VI: Chinese Materials, 1900-1954
Scope and Content Note
Chiefly records of the A.S. Henderson general merchandise store in Patagonia, Arizona, from 1900 to 1940 including inventories, correspondence, merchandise ads, ledgers, monthly account books, and bills. His mining interests are represented by correspondence with Josiah Bond and John F. Campbell; legal papers; assay and ore reports; and notices of numerous mines in Santa Cruz County. A photograph album depicts the mine buildings and personnel of the Black Bonanza Mine. Real estate ventures were mainly in the Patagonia area and California. His investments include mainly oil and gas leases in Texas. Personal items for him include correspondence, portraits, bank statements, health books, automobile information, and documents relating to his position on the Santa Cruz County Board of Supervisors.
Eva Henderson materials include personal correspondence with pioneer relatives in Oklahoma; also books, certificates, photos, and other items related to her educational and professional osteopath activities in Oklahoma and Arizona. Minnie Stevens materials include a musical composition, a diary, photos, and typescripts on Oklahoma land claim shanties.
Personal and business activities of Chinese merchants in Patagonia are documented by files of Woo Ben, Louis Kang, Sam Thomas, and Tom Wegin and include holograph notebooks and letters in Chinese characters, and printed items concerned with fortune-telling, literature, philosophy, and medicine. These materials were found in the leased section of the Henderson store.
Most material is in English, some in Chinese.
Henderson, Alexander S., 1859-1944 -- Archives; Henderson, Eva, 1871-1965 -- Archives; Stevens, Minnie Rosilla; Bond, Josiah; Campbell, John F.; Kang, Louis; Thomas, Sam; Ben, Woo; Wegin, Tom; Frontier and pioneer life -- Arizona -- Santa Cruz County; Frontier and pioneer life -- Oklahoma; Women pioneers; Chinese -- Arizona -- Patagonia -- History; Chinese Americans -- Photographs; Merchants -- Arizona -- Patagonia -- History; Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- History; Mine buildings -- Arizona -- Santa Cruz County -- Photographs; Fortune-telling; Osteopathic medicine -- History; Retail trade -- Arizona -- History; Santa Cruz County (Ariz.) -- Politics and government; Patagonia (Ariz.) -- History; Black Bonanza Mine (Ariz.); Account books; Correspondence; Photographs
Container List
- Series I: A.S. Henderson Store Records, 1907-1940
  - Cash Book. January 1909-October 1914 (Volume 1)
  - Ledger. 1909 (Volume 2)
  - Journal. October 1911-1916 (Volume 3)
  - Journal. 1916-1923 (Volume 4)
  - Store financial records: 3 ledgers. 1911-1912 (Box 5)
  - Store financial records: Wholesale accounts. (Box 5)
  - Store financial records: Cost sale price-book. 1911-1913 (Box 5)
  - Store financial records: Monthly accounts. 1909, 1911-1914 (Box 5)
  - Monthly accounts (four books). 1916-1917 (Box 6)
  - Monthly accounts (13 books & envelopes). 1918-1940 (Box 7)
  - Store financial records: invoice register. 1908-1909 (Box 8)
  - Store financial records: cost price book. (Box 8)
  - Store financial records: notarial record book. 1907-1909 (Box 8)
  - Store financial records: inventories. (Box 8)
  - Store financial records: 2 folders of miscellaneous accounts. (Box 8)
  - Store correspondence. 1909-1930 (Box 9)
  - Store bills: various. 1909-1934 (Box 10, Folder 1-5)
  - Store bills: J.A. Dick, El Paso. 1911-1925 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Store bills: Escalad Brothers, Nogales. 1914-1934 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Store bills: B. Maier & Co., Benson. 1915-1928 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Store bills: Murray & Layne Co., Deming, NM. 1920-1925 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Store bills: Albert Steinfeld & Co., Tucson. 1912-1925 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Store miscellany: merchandise orders on Henderson store. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Store miscellany: advertisements (calendars, blotters, notebooks, almanacs, etc.). (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Store miscellany: ads, trade journals, revenue stamps, letterhead paper, etc. (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (A-K): canvas goods. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (A-K): clothing. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (A-K): construction materials (fences, roofing, paint, floor-covering). (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (A-K): food. (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (A-K): furnaces and heating equipment. (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (A-K): hardware and machinery. (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (A-K): hats. (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (A-K): household supplies and equipment. (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (L-Z): lamps and lighting. (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (L-Z): saddlery, harnesses, wagons. (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (L-Z): shoes. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (L-Z): seed catalog. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (L-Z): miscellaneous. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Store Merchandise Ads (L-Z): Marconi Velvet Tone Disc Records ("For sale by Henderson & Johnson, Patagonia, Arizona"). (Box 13)
- Series II: Mining Records and Correspondence, 1911-1954
  - General. 1912-1913 (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
  - Josiah Bond. 1914-1933 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Phelps Dodge Corporation. 1913, 1926-1935 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - John F. Campbell and wife. 1912-1954 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Arizona Lyrics (magazine of verse written and published by Josiah Bond at Alto, Arizona). 1921-1924 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Notice of mining location. (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Harshaw mining district. (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Patagonia mining district (Golden State mine). (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Patagonia mining district. (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Tyndall mining district (Alto mines group). (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Tyndall mining district (Jefferson mine, Baca float. (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Tyndall mining district. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Wrightstown mining district. (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous mining papers. (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Ore settlements (Consolidated Kansas City Smelting & Refining Co.). 1911-1925 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Ore settlements (American Smelting & Refining Co.). 1925-1939 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Ore settlements (Phelps Dodge Corporation). 1926-1930 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Assay Reports (American Smelting & Refining Co.). 1926-1941 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Assay Reports (Hugo Miller, Nogales). 1914-1940 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Assay Reports (various). 1913-1947 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Ore shipments. 1925-1934 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Bills. 1918-1942 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Black Bonanza mine. (Box 16, Folder 9)
- Series III: Property Records and Investments, 1900-1963
  - Arizona Property: Patagonia property (including Henderson store). (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Arizona Property: Henderson Ranch. 1900-1959 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Arizona Property: Private road crossing at Crittenden. 1924-1928, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Arizona Property: Rent Receipts. 1915-1961 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Arizona Property: Santa Cruz County Taxes. 1913-1959 (Box 17, Folder 5-7)
  - Arizona Property: Grazing permits. 1913-1931 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Arizona Property: Insurance (Patagonia property). 1933-1958 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Out of State Property: California property, Atascadero (legal papers, correspondence). 1913-1956 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Out of State Property: California property, Atascadero (taxes). 1917-1957 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Out of State Property: California property, Palos Verdes Estates. 1925-1950 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Out of State Property: California Property, Lost Angeles County (taxes). 1925-1954 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Out of State Property: California Property, Washington Home Park. 1917-1955 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Out of State Property: Oklahoma property (legal papers, taxes, etc.). 1912-1941 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Out of State Property: Texas property (legal papers, taxes.). 1914-1942 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Out of State Property: Miscellaneous legal papers. (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Investments: Burnham Chemical Company. 1924-1957 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Investments: Oil and Gas Leases (New Mexico). 1943-1963 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Investments: Oil and Gas Leases (Texas, Louisiana, Mississippi). (Box 19, Folder 3-6)
  - Investments: miscellaneous investments (mining, aircraft, tire & rubber, real estate, bonds, etc.). (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Banks: Consolidated National Bank, Tucson (various papers). 1912-1916 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Banks: First National Bank, Nogales (statements). 1908-1945 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Banks: First State Bank, Patagonia (statements). 1918-1923 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Banks: Nogales National Bank, Nogales (statements). 1923-1927 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Banks: Sonora Bank and Trust Co., Nogales (various papers). 1923-1928 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Banks: Valley National Bank, Nogales (statements). 1945-1947 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Banks: Correspondence and miscellaneous material (various banks). (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Banks: miscellaneous financial records. (Box 20, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Alexander S. Henderson, Personal Materials, 1899-1958
  - Correspondence: ASH and Eva. 1914-1943 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence: various relatives. 1905-1944 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: miscellaneous. 1899-1944 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: pension. 1921-1945 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of ASH. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Personal miscellany. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Estate of A.S. Henderson. 1944-1952 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Santa Cruz County. Board of Supervisors. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Patagonia Chamber of Commerce. 1919-1920 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Automobile material. 1914-1958 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Automobile material (ads). 1915-1937 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Ralston Gardens of Life: A study of health and the best way of living...Ralston Health Club, by Edmund Shaftesbury, Washington, D.C. 1900 (Box 22)
  - Book of General Membership of the Ralston Health Club. 1900 (Box 22)
- Series V: Eva Henderson, Personal Materials, 1888-1961
  - Letters from Minnie Stevens (sister). 1907-1940 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
  - Letters from Mother. 1908-1939 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Letters from Father. 1908-1917 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Cal Stevens (brother) and his wife. 1907-1955 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Letters from other relatives. 1922-1954 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous bills and receipts. 1937-1960 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Regarding the estate of Lorance E. Stevens (mother). (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Minnie Stevens (sister). 1905 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Minnie Stevens (sister): musical composition. (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Personal Miscellany. (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence. 1908-1961 (Box 24, Folder 2-3)
  - Patagonia Ice and Light Company (utility rate uproar). 1948-1949 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Photographs. (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Bible Readings for the Home Circle (Seventh-Day Adventist). 1888 (Box 24)
  - Notebook, containing financial records. 1946-1954 (Box 24)
  - Osteopathy Material: American School of Osteopathy. 1900-1902 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Osteopathy Material: Arizona State Osteopathic Board, State Dept. of Health, registration papers. 1924-1959 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Osteopathy Material: Arizona Society of Osteopathic Physicians and Surgeons. 1949-1956 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Osteopathy Material: miscellaneous material on Osteopathy and Health. (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Osteopathy Material: Journal of Osteopathy, (Kirksville, MO). 1901 (Box 25)
  - Osteopathy Material: Philosophy of Osteopathy, by Andrew T. Still, Kirksville, MO. 1899 (Box 25)
- Series VI: Chinese Materials, 1900-1954
  - Patagonia property, lot 16, block A (legal papers). 1901-1902, 1929-1930, 1942 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Woo Ben: correspondence. 1935-1937 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Woo Ben: correspondence (family). 1902-1934 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Woo Ben: correspondence (mining). 1900-1909 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Woo Ben: Bonnie Carie & Gray Eagle Mines (legal papers). 1900-1914 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Woo Ben: notebooks. (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Louis Kang: correspondence. (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Louis Kang: Santa Cruz County, Texas. 1903-1938 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Sam Thomas: correspondence. (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Sam Thomas: financial papers. 1939-1948 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  - Tom Wegin: miscellaneous material (correspondence, bills, etc.). (Box 26, Folder 11)
  - Tom Wegin: store records. 1944-1954 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Tom Wegin: bank records. 1945-1949 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  - Various printed and holograph items. (Box 27)
    Includes the following:
    Fortune Telling with Numbers. New Continent Library (Chinese), 1926
    Types of Hand Machines (Chinese).
    Notebook: clippings and notes of a political nature.
    Two Fortune-telling notebooks (Chinese).
    Fortune-telling handbook (Chinese).
    Monthly literary magazine, published in Hong Kong and Canton (Chinese).
    Mail Boat Rates in China (Chinese), 1919
    Metals, published in Hong Kong (Chinese), 1917
    The Youth's Magazine, vol.VI, not.9, published by the Commercial Press, Shanghai (Chinese), September 20, 1917
    Poetry notebook (Chinese).
    A Collection of Medicine Distributors and Providers of Urgently needed Prescriptions, published by C.T.Sun, Los Angeles (Chinese).
    A Look at my Life, philosophical text (Chinese).
    Newspapers.
  - Oversize Material. (Box 28)
    Marriage Certificate, A.S. Henderson and Eva Stevens, Patagonia, AZ, December 31, 1907
    Degree of Doctor of Osteopathy, American School of Osteopathy, Kirksville, MO, to Eva Stevens, June 26, 1902
    Two Osteopath's certificates, Oklahoma, for Eva Stevens, July 7, 1903 and January 4, 1908